Chicago Ethnic Arts Project collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 6: Sound Recordings, 1977
  - Subseries 13: White Southerners
    - Church service at Northside United Pentecostal Church, Chicago, Illinois, part 1-4, July 17, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20782 - AFS 20785; RXA 1079-1082; 4 audiotape reel, 7 in.
      Part 1 of a 4-part recording of the Sunday service at Northside Pentecostal Church, 1527 E. Edgewater Ave. in the Edgewater neighborhood; the leader and pastor was Bobby Goddard; recorded on a stereo Nagra IV with a Sennheiser 402 microphone at the pulpit and, for most of the recording, a second Sennheiser 402 directed toward the congregation, with some variation as noted; this part includes Goddard's greetings, and a prayer with voiced heard from the congregation; song "We're together again," led by Paul Dean and Joann Bolen, both with vocal and guitar; hymn "I'll be Somewhere Listening to My Name" (number 25 in the hymnal Pentecostal Praises) led at the pulpit by a woman with Goddard standing behind her and singing as well; hymn "The Fullness of Godhead is all in Him" (number 29); Goddard makes a birthday call and a a boy and girl come forward and drop one penny for each year into a glass, as BG rings a little bell, congregation then sings "Happy Birthday to You"; Goddard states a welcome and transitions to Sunday School; Paul Dean remarks on the making of this recording (right channel only, the fieldworker then moves one microphone); Dean begins the adult Sunday School lesson, preceded by a hymn duet by Dean and Bolen (right channel), both playing guitars, "What a Glorious Day that Will Be"; Dean's Sunday School lesson, about the Pentecostal doctrine concerning speaking in tongues, baptism, and the doctrine of the Trinity (right channel only); Dean's lesson continues in part 2. Part 2 of a 4-part recording of the Sunday service at Northside Pentecostal Church, 1527 E. Edgewater Ave. in the Edgewater neighborhood; the leader and pastor was Bobby Goddard; recorded on a stereo Nagra IV with a Sennheiser 402 microphone at the pulpit and, for most of the recording, a second Sennheiser 402 directed toward the congregation, with some variation as noted; this part continues Paul Dean's Sunday School lesson from part 1, on the right channel only, which continues in part 3. Part 3 of a 4-part recording of the Sunday service at Northside Pentecostal Church, 1527 E. Edgewater Ave. in the Edgewater neighborhood; the leader and pastor was Bobby Goddard; recorded on a stereo Nagra IV with a Sennheiser 402 microphone at the pulpit and, for most of the recording, a second Sennheiser 402 directed toward the congregation, with some variation as noted; the first segment in this part continues Paul Dean's Sunday School lesson from part 2, on the right channel only; the second segment records Goddard's remarks from the pulpit that conclude the Sunday School lesson, on left channel with the right channel microphone again directed at the congregation; hymn "Oyer in the Gloryland" (number 140 in the hymnal Pentecostal Praises); led by Goddard and followed by his call for offerings; prayer from a congregant (name may be Brother Gregory), right channel only; offering hymn "You can't Outgive the Lord"; Goddard makes remarks no giving; duet by Joann Bolen, with guitar, and another woman, both standing behind pulpit with audio on both channels, "There'll be change after while"; children led by "Miss Debby" come up front and sing, right channel only, preceded by introduction by Goddard Debby, sing "Little Red Box," "There was a man who died for us and Jesus was his name, J-E-S-U-S," and "God is not Dead, He is still A1ive"; next is Goddard's sermon "Truth or Tradition," with live recording microphone on the left, while the public address system mixes with the congregational response on the right, with delay at the start as the right microphone is repositioned and its module is switched from 402 to 802. The tape runs out during the sermon, recording continues in part 4. Part 4 of a 4-part recording of the Sunday service at Northside Pentecostal Church, 1527 E. Edgewater Ave. in the Edgewater neighborhood; the leader and pastor was Bobby Goddard; recorded on a stereo Nagra IV with a Sennheiser 402 microphone at the pulpit and, for most of the recording, a second Sennheiser 402 directed toward the congregation, with some variation as noted; the first segment in this part continues Goddard's sermon from part 3; next segment is the closing prayer, with many voices speaking aloud and independently, with Goddard on the left channel and the congregation on the right, dominated by the voice of Paul Dean due to his proximity to the microphone; then an ending announcement, and for a bit, the tape continues to roll.
    - Interview and country music performances by Johnny Grey, a steel mill worker from Alabama, Chicago, Illinois, part 1-2, May 18, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20786A - AFS 20786B; RYA 0784; 2 audiocassette, C-60
      Part 1 of a 2-part recording of steel mill worker Johnny Grey (Johnny Gray ?) made by folklorist Ben Sandmel in the Quiet Knight nightclub, 953 W. Belmont Ave. in the Lake View neighborhood; Grey is originally from Berry (Barry?) Alabama, and lives in the Uptown neighborhood; in this recording, Grey sings and accompanies himself on guitar on "Wedding Bells," comments on how he went to jail young, and at age 16 was obliged to quit school and find a job; "Tonight I Just Don't give a Damn," more biographical comments; "This Time I Hurt her More than She Hurt me," how Grey's parents were separated when he was young; "She Thinks I Still Care," "Jimmy Brown the Newsboy," a fragment on guitar, "Here I am, I'm Drunk Again," Grey's recollection of going to Nashville and playing from club to club, including George Jones's club in Printers Alley, how he sang at Tootsies Orchid Lounge and was complimented by Grant Turner, Grey would like to go to Nashville permanently; "Jimmy Brown the Newsboy," as instrumental, how Grey attended a bluegrass festival in Ottawa Ohio; "God Gave You to Me," about Luke Hagv (Hagee, Hagie, Hagy ?), another Uptown musician, plays banjo like Ralph Stanley; Grey plays an unidentified instrumental not unlike "Freight Train"; fragment of a tune often called "The Promised Land," discussion of playing in bars, and about Chicago musicians. Part 2 of a 2-part recording of steel mill worker Johnny Grey (Johnny Gray ?) made by folklorist Ben Sandmel in the Quiet Knight nightclub, 953 W. Belmont Ave. in the Lake View neighborhood; Grey is originally from Berry (Barry?) Alabama, and lives in the Uptown neighborhood; in this recording, Grey discusses the make-up of the ideal band, number of instruments, twin fiddles; then sings and accompanies himself on guitar on "I Saw the Light"; duration of this recording is less than 5 minutes.
    - Interview with Reverend Bobby Goddard in his home, Chicago, Illinois, July 19, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20787; RYA 0785; audiocassette, C-60
      Interview with Pentecostal preacher Bobby Goddard at his home, 2506 W. Hutchison St. in the North Center neighborhood, relating to his life and to the Northside Pentecostal Church; Goddard is from Raleigh County, West Virginia; about Paul Dean, also a leader of Northside church, Dean had been in the Assemblies of God denomination for thirty years prior to joining Northside; about Joann Bolen and her husband, from Beckley WV; other members of the church have connections back to Tennessee, Kentucky, and Alabama; fieldworker moves the microphone, clips to Goddard's shirt; Goddard explains that he has been the Northside pastor for seven years, he and another man started with a storefront; the current building had been Lutheran, the Church of God, now Pentecostal; Goddard's storefront church had been in the 2300 block of Lincoln Ave near Fullerton; in the neighborhood south of Lake View (Lincoln Park ?); Goddard's home is on the western side of Lake View; Goddard says that the Northside members come from every part of Chicago, more from Lake View, Uptown, and Rogers Park; Goddard has a bus he uses to bring people to church, its route includes Albany Park, Lake View, Uptown, sometime he stops as specific homes, sometimes at street corners; the van will carry up to 42 people, including children; Goddard is working on getting a larger bus into operation; Goddard was 28 when he came to Chicago in 1959, married no children; had been truck driver at coal mines but they were shutting down; Goddard arrived in a Sunday and met his brother the next day, then got a job in a gasket factory in Skokie, four and half miles away; about people going back to the South, Goddard said, "Oh yes, that's why we have such a small church, our people all head back South"; there is also a great movement to the suburbs, suburban Pentecostal churches are the only ones growing today; about the "sections" of Goddard's branch of Pentecostalism, Illinois has 12 sections; 17 churches in Chicago and near suburbs with average of from 50-70 members, although one has 350; about Uptown, as a neighborhood from migrants from the South over time, Goddard remembers arriving and hopes to move before long; about his feelings about Raleigh County, "my heart is set on the work of God, I feel Chicago is the greatest mission field in the entire world"; Goddard's mother and wife's parents still in WV; how Goddard hopes the church will grow and he will be able to quit his job; about the call the be preacher, Goddard felt it strongly, "the Bible became real to me, as if I'm living with the Apostles"; Goddard says that he outlines his sermons, he sits by himself and thoughts come to him, inspired by God, he jots notes on paper, the starting point is always a Bible verse; Goddard studies the Bible, and a concordance, late at night, certain verses become real to him; how the Lord used material things to bring about the spiritual; Goddard had been raised as a Baptist; when preaching now, sometimes he gets in the spirit and the notes are set aside; how members get anointed and words come fast; about mastering the skill to preach, role of experience.
  - Subseries 14: Polish
    - Interview with Alvin and Jeannette Sajewski in their store about Polish music and traditions, Chicago, Illinois, part 1-4, June 02, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20788A - AFS 20789B; RYA 0786 - 0787; 4 audiocassette, C-60
      Part 1 of a 4-part interview with sister and brother Jania Sajewski (Jeanette Sajewski Terley or Jeannette Sajewski Terlikowski) and Alvin Sajewski in their music store, 1227 Milwaukee Ave; about contacts to visit, Jeanette recommends Fr. Donald Bilinski (Polish Museum of America), the Daily Zgoda, and Dr. Bzienski; then discussion of how local musicians come to the store, mostly polka orchestra members, long tradition of Polish music in the Chicago area and polka is at its height, even with young people; polka has been here from the time of the first settlers; the old timers played by ear, violin, clarinet, coronet, button accordions; music was an important part of leisure time, songs were passed on through the generations; how groups were formed to play at weddings and other functions, first informal, later with more training, some were composers; Polish and English translations were used; Jeanette and Alvin know most of musicians in the Polish tradition in the area; Alvin describes how they [including his father Wladyslaw] helped musicians get their start, how they helped the recording companies with advice; we grew up with the cylinder records, folks wanted Polish music if they were to purchase phonographs, the Sajewskis agreed to stock and sell phonographs if Polish records were made, then they helped the musicians produce the records, also published sheet music, what the people wanted generated the demand; Frank Przybylski worked with their father; he would transcribe a tune from the person who knew it and then it would be printed, also songs were composed for special events; this all started around 1910 or 1911; Alvin describes immigration to Chicago, how people lived when they arrived, churches were formed, there was a need for a gathering place such as a church hall, life centered around the parish, music including hymns were common; St. Joseph's day was important; Sajewski published hymns too, and songs in Polish for Mother's Day; music would be used by the parochial schools, for example, in programs for the mothers, or the pastor's name day or mother superior's name day; Alvin says "It all starts with that little church first"; then comes the need for schools, English and Polish in them, children participated; how the Sajewski's music business was involved because of the needs generated by the schools, Polish songs for the first graders; this was 25 years ago, all in Polish, not so much now; but today Polish is offered in some schools, as well as in ethnic community Saturday schools; there are important Polish fraternal organizations such as the Polish National Alliance (PNA), the Polish Roman Catholic Union (PRCU), the Polish Wornen's Alliance, all wish to teach children Polish; Polonia (Polish Chicago) is on the south side, around 47th and Ashland, and in Sajewski's neighborhood; the music store also published Polish plays from 1910-15 to about 1930-34, performances in parishes, fundraiser like carnivals, ways for the young people to get money for the parish; before WWII there was not much outside entertainment, comments about the kinds of entertainment in Polonia before the war; about young people's activities, their social life, the ways boys met girls; there were masses for the children daily, also various societies in the parishes, e.g., the St. Ann's Society for women, others for young people; there were plays in Polish for 6th grade and up, and graduation songs, and there were "mock" Polish weddings, a staged event with invitations to parishioners so they could participate, discussion of mock weddings continues in part 2. Part 2 of a 4-part interview with sister and brother Jania Sajewski (Jeanette Sajewski Terley or Jeannette Sajewski Terlikowski) and Alvin Sajewski in their music store, 1227 Milwaukee Ave; about mock weddings, continued from part 1was a great money maker; folks paid for the food, there would be a traditional bride dance and folks would try to break plates by throwing silver dollars at them; another activity was the Polish minstrel show where people would dress in oriental costumes but speak Polish; these were run by parishes and not by professional entertainers, people could get their start this way, later some might become professional actors and actresses; song fests were big and Sajewski's published sheet music and books for these; today, Sajewski publishes polka music and books, most for popular dancing; Alvin says nowadays, "If they play an oberek [dance genre], they dance a polka to it"; piano became popular around 1905 or so, and very popular around 1910-15, families bought them, everybody wanted sewing machines too, sold door to door from carts, then sheet music was wanted, Sajewski published same; player piano rolls came out about 1919 or earlier and were desirable; Poles and other ethnic groups wanted piano rolls and created the demand; most worked at International Harvester or Pullman, the store carried the pianos but needed rolls in other languages; Alvin's father Wladyslaw approached the U.S. Music Roll Company about to making Polish piano rolls, they wouldn't, so he paid in advance and, in time, there were 140 Sajewski Specials; another company was QRS Piano Rolls and they began printing the words on the rolls; funeral homes wanted music to play in the background during funerals, and they approached Sajewski the record companies to produce these in Polish but could not offer large enough sales, some funeral homes did experiment with Polish records but it was not a success, the songs upset the Polish patrons, people would associate the songs with the death of loved ones and get upset whenever they'd hear that song; Jeanette shows instruction books Sajewski did for piano players in Polish and English, there were also used by teachers; some books are for choirs; these have Easter and Christmas hymns in them, sold to Churches and to people who used them at home; there is a sing-along book with popular old time Polish songs called the Radio Songbook because a radio show advertised the book, first published around 1943; Sajewski's advertised on Polish radio shows; Jeanette says doctors recommended during WWII that depressed persons listen to music, and songs from previous wars were recycled; Jeanette shows the latest polka books, musicians used to need music for each instrument but now music is mostly read, so just need two, C and B-flat; Sajewski is very proud of their dance instruction book for national Polish dances, with charts for dances, music, and information about each dance, used in dance schools in the U.S. and other nations; there are records with the book, music played by the man who created the book, he was born in Poland; Jeanette shows a record that was a great hit with the American public, recorded by many artists including Bobby Vinton, every daddy sang it to his daughter; Stephen J. Zielinski composed the lyrics and Frank Przybylski the music; about immigrants after WWII, Jeanette says they had their culture started and were not lonesome for the home country like the folks who came in the 1910s who clung together and whose hearts were linked to those left behind; post-WWII the immigrants were already displaced from camps and other places, simply alive and glad to be so, they wanted to fit themselves into this country or any they came to live in, they have more "international desire" and adapted more; some do come to the store for modern music imported from Poland, and classical music, and for folk songs done by choirs with ballet companies; Jeanette appreciates these forms of music for the beauty but it does not have the strength the country music did; Sajewskis have obtained records from Poland since 1914-18, and through WWII. and now they get it in greater volume, classical, rock and roll, jazz, folk songs, ballads, all modern and in Polish, but Americans don't buy the jazz or rock and roll since they have their own; some young people do buy it out of curiosity, and some buy it for their relatives in Poland. Part 3 of a 4-part interview with sister and brother Jania Sajewski (Jeanette Sajewski Terley or Jeannette Sajewski Terlikowski) and Alvin Sajewski in their music store, 1227 Milwaukee Ave; about the recent banquet honoring Sajewski, and about its program, which includes a list of people Sajewski family helped to record; Jeanette compiled the book; about the 9 children, 5 boys and 4 girls, and how they all worked in the store as children; they lived over the store, their dad Wladyslaw built a store at 1017 Milwaukee Ave. for the family, with a 12 room apartment that offered 5 bedrooms, 2 living rooms, a laundry room, kitchen, dining room; the store had custom built oak cabinets and they were moved to the current store, Jeanette says, "And we cherish these memories, it's been a whole lifetime, two lifetimes, dad's and ours"; why and how they talked Alvin into the testimonial dinner to celebrate the 80 years of Sajewski's store; Alvin talks about his trip to Washington, DC [to the American Folklife Center's 1977 Ethnic Recordings in America conference], one of the happiest days of his life; about forgetting his heart medicine, about meeting Myron Surmach and their long acquaintance by mail; about a book of speeches also published by Sajewski for name days or other occasions; a model to teach public speaking; more about the Polish dance book (discussed in part 2), how Wladyslaw had gone to Poland to find such a book but could not, he returned and told his two colleagues they would have to write one, so one got the music ready and the other took little dolls in costume and set up a stage and moved them through the dances, in order to work out the figures of the dance, charts of which are drawn by hand; Alvin discusses how his father organized the first travel excursion to Poland after WWI in 1927, when Lindbergh was f lying across the ocean, they went by the ship Ile de France from Chicago, Wladyslaw had organized the Polish Businessman's Association and they sponsored the trip, which cost about $300, the wine on the ship was special because it was prohibition in the U.S.; their mother went on the second excursion; Alvin has never been to Poland and has no desire to go, he has no relatives there, and has little time for travel; Christmas is a rush time in the store and family members come to help out, otherwise he and Jeanette manage well; each of the other brothers grew out of the store, two became pharmacists; Alvin went to high school and business college but worked with his father all the time; the other siblings wanted to do other things; by 1919-1920, he was his father's right hand man; Wladyslaw died in 1948 but was active until the end; he remembers that on a Saturday they finished in the store and were joking with each other, Alvin went home and his father went upstairs, then on Sunday they went to a Polish play at Holy Trinity school, and his dad died in his seat there, his head fell onto their mother's shoulder, it was April 14, he was waiting for the curtain to go up, everyone there was a friend, a Polish radio announcer carried him out, he never regained consciousness; they had worked as a team and many times since, Alvin has felt his father's presence in the store; especially when he has to make difficult decisions, mention the Polish National Alliance (PNA) building dedication on the coming weekend; Jeanette and Alvin show things from the testimonial dinner, one from the Polish Disc Jockey's Association; Jeanette tells how important it was to her to have this event; there are certificates from the International Polka Association, from the Polish American Press, document from the Pope, in Polish, an electric clock with the Polish musicians' names on it, the bandleader Walter "Li'l Wally" Jagiello sent a floral piece; there were displays on a table at the hall with photos and records, catalogs from the early days, assembled by a brother and brother-in-law; discussion of the displays con
    - Interview with Wanda Krozel about Polish crafts, Chicago, Illinois, part 1-2, June 02, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20790A - AFS 20790B; RYA 0788; 2 audiocassette, C-60